hi welcome back to the lum rim
and today we're going to do a review of
the whole course
uh it's good for me i i would i i would
like to do a review myself you know this
format of doing separate episodes
and then uh doing them at separate times
you kind of lose the flow of the whole
teaching so i thought it would be nice
today if we went back from the beginning
and we went through the flow of the
whole alum rim teaching that we had
now i'm going to do that flow based on
the idioms
on the idea images that we use
to teach the aci teachers so the aci
teachers
are expected to be able to look at one
of these pictures
and identify the idea behind it and i
think
tim how may we said like there's going
to be a thousand or something
how many
500 something like that so it's kind of
easy to take an exam
to to examine someone
just based on the pictures so we just
throw these pictures at you
so i challenge you uh during this review
when we throw up a picture then you know
tell i'll give you a second and see if
you can
remember what the picture was about okay
and this is a good review
of the entire uh course that we're doing
all right here we go
first picture mr cd
uh this picture is supposed to remind
you
that there uh we are in the middle of
the practices for people of medium
capacity
and what they're trying to get to is
nirvana
they're trying to get out of the wheel
of life out of all suffering
for themselves personally and
this is where buddha taught the three
trainings
that will help you to reach your
personal nirvana
the third training is understanding
emptiness
understanding the pen the second
training
is meditation and on a deep level these
two
can only be done you know in a quiet
place
during certain times of the day when
you're really focusing
on your meditation mat and on a deep
level
uh these two cannot they have to be done
on special periods of the day
but this one uh the foundation for those
two which is being nice to other people
okay you can call it morality you could
call it an ethical way of life
but in the end it's being nice to other
people
okay that's the foundation which is
always available to us all day long
so this is one of the three
extraordinary trainings
of buddhism meant to help us to reach
nirvana
and it's available to us all day long so
in this picture uh you can see seiji
helping geshe michael to figure out
his computer which is one of the nicest
things that young people can do for
older people all right next
picture see if you can remember what
this picture was
did you guess this lady is doing her
taxes
okay and what does that make her
in this slum-rim system it makes her
a dharma master okay so
when i say dharma master tantric master
i know the picture you have in your mind
it's a some big llama
up on the throne and they have a big
yellow hat maybe they are
ringing a bell and a little drum and
they are
bruh old or girls or something
and you think oh that's a diamond master
that's a real darn master or you're
thinking of that old picture of
nagarjuna
and you know he's he's all kind of
mystical
but really in the long rim what we
learned
was this this uh woman uh who
you know she has a couple kids she's
married and
she's a dharma master okay she is a real
dharma master
so pobunku and chase said don't think
that a dharma master has to be sitting
up on a throne
and you know reciting some tantric
ritual this lady
is doing what she's paying
taxes okay which is you know
to be honest on your taxes is like
really difficult
in my country you know it might take you
weeks to do your taxes and
and to really do them carefully uh to do
them completely honestly
to pay every single penny you're
supposed to pay this
makes her she has the first of the
extraordinary trainings
of a good good person kind to other
people
and that makes her a real dharma master
okay so forget those
pictures you have of llamas with big
hats on and
ringing bells okay that's easy anybody
can do that
uh to to be nice to people is difficult
okay and to and to keep your morality to
keep your ethics
is also difficult okay next one
uh this
is i'll give you a moment do you
remember what this is about
the quotation in the long run was such a
good
a person who's really keeping their vows
really keeping their buddhist guidelines
the 10
guidelines especially they shine
they actually shine a person who's
making a healthy
modest you know low-key
effort to keep their commitments uh keep
the ten
uh good karmas be nice to other people
then they have some kind of a peaceful
look on their face
they are shining and when they walk into
a room you know it
everyone starts feeling better you know
so like tim and siji
so uh that's the light of the world
buddha said
those people are the light of the world
okay
and there's a christian expression uh
don't put a candle
under a basket you know like let the
world see your happy face
and and that's a light it's a it's a
it's a true guiding light for the whole
world okay
next picture number four
where are we yeah this is uh
a cliff that i went on uh with uh
with my partner veronica for her
birthday uh
during this alarm room and uh
they were talking about the sun
setting which in tibetan the word is
nupa
it's also the word for west because the
sun sets in the west so nupa means
the sun setting and this is a very sad
verb this is a very sad idea
uh in the dharma and it the most famous
place comes at the end of the abhidharma
kosha
the treasure house of higher wisdom
treasure house of higher knowledge
by master vasabandhu and he says
the the dharma the sun of the dharma the
light of the dharma
will set in this world we will lose the
light of the dharma in this world
this world will go into darkness okay
after a certain amount of time
the teachings of the buddha will
disappear in this world
first they disappear in the minds of
people
and then but they're still in libraries
those books are still in libraries
probably libraries that john brady
hasn't found yet
and then later uh they will disappear
from the libraries also and then they'll
be gone
now i put the picture here because
paboka but
made a special point and he said
if you can't keep your commitments if
you can't keep
nice behavior towards other people then
we can say the dharma has left this
world
the light of the dharma has left this
world inside of you
okay the sun has set inside your own
chest which would be a very sad thing
okay if we don't keep our vows
okay next picture
[Music]
yeah we called this retreat loving the
time of the virus
and the point was
that during a very difficult time in the
world
if you keep your commitments if you are
nice
to other people when things are
frightening
scary the virus is spreading we don't
know where we don't know
how we don't know how many people will
die
and if during those difficult times
you do something nice to other people
it's much much more powerful
and he mentioned if you remember a
five-star buddha paradise
which is like a perfect perfect place
it's
easy to be a good person everybody there
is a good person
that's no big achievement okay that's
not a big deal and the seed is not that
powerful
to be nice in a group of nice people
okay to be nice
when people are attacking you when
people are afraid
uh when people are not being nice to
each other to be the one person
who stands up and shares things
in a difficult time then that's an
extremely pure person that's a great
karma
that's an incredible karma much more
powerful so i think this
virus is a very good time it's a very
good chance for all of us
to show are we really buddhists
okay are we are we really practicing the
bodhisattva
okay can we help others even when things
are very hard
okay all right next picture
this one is hard to remember i have
trouble remember it i'm going to give
you a second to try to think of what
this picture is
okay papangarimpuche was quoting some
books
very very common ending to different
he quoted one famous one which is los
angeles los angeles
it means made the
teachings of the victorious one
uh los angeles spread
in this world and then you know you're
thinking
oh you know we gotta get on the internet
we've got to translate this alarm
into many languages we have to try to
spread
the good word to as many people as we
can
and that's the end of the prayer that's
what we're supposed to we're supposed to
walk
out of this lomrium class or video
and we're supposed to share the dharma
with
other people and we're supposed to
spread the dharma in the world
and in this part of the lamrim
said look the place you're supposed to
spread the dharma
is here inside your own heart okay
so don't think of spreading the dharma
means you know
try to translate the videos into more
languages or something like that that's
a very important spreading of the dharma
but he says if you spread it in your own
heart
then of course it will spread outside of
you because the world is coming from
your heart
okay from your heart chakra actually
okay next
picture number seven
try to remember what this picture was
about i'll give you a second
yeah and this is i don't know this is a
favorite topic of mine
uh having a personal relationship
uh with another person uh you know
like these two people have uh
in my opinion and in tantra it's one of
the happiest things that can happen to
you
it's one of the greatest things that can
happen to you
it's it's anybody can tell you
the reason the whole world is looking
for a partner
is that it makes people happy it's one
of the greatest happinesses
when it's going well it's one of the
greatest happinesses you can have
but you know and you you know and i know
when it's not going well it's one of the
greatest miseries
in life why is that relevant to this
course right here
uh if you're if your morality
is good it's the happiest thing in your
life
and if you break your morality it's the
same thing it's going to make you
miserable it's like having a nice
woman or man who's your partner uh the
same person
who makes you totally happy can also
make you totally miserable
so in this case uh vinaya your personal
practice
of kindness good behavior is being
compared to a partner
who can either make you be the best
thing in your life
or the worst thing in your life same
person okay all right next
in um number eight i think
uh this was a complicated one see if you
can remember
i'll take a sip of my green drink
thanks vimela
[Music]
this guy this actually represents
breaking your commitments okay
this pulling up a weed okay
uh represents uh breaking your
commitments why
i mean destroying this plant uh it's
breaking
your commitment and if you're a gardener
you know that you should pull a weed out
before the seeds are ready okay if you
wait
until the seeds are ready to drop off
and then you pull the plant out then
you're going to
spread about a thousand seeds for next
next month or next year you're going to
get thousands of weeds growing back so
you have to attack those weeds early
okay
this refers to a very radical statement
that buddha made ke long talk song
tells
it's better to die than to break your
vows
why when you break your vows
you are setting in motion seeds
which will continue to fall off for many
lifetimes
okay so if you die you ruin
one body mind complex you know if you
die
you ruin one very useful
temple a physical temple and a mine you
you lose
one but if you break your commitment
you lose many uh body mind body mind
complexes you ruin your body and mind
for many lifetimes
and you kind of set seeds into motion
which are going to ruin many lifetimes
so you know buddha was saying
it's better to die than to break your
vows and and he was
not being metaphorical he was he was
speaking
very uh literally when he said that
better to die than to break your
commitments okay
then there's a joke in the alarm room
you know we take a vow never to give up
bodhichitta even at the cost of our
lives
and there's a famous statement that
so all through our whole life we're
waiting
to get put into prison by some evil
people
and they come up with a knife and they
say okay give up your body stuff about
or die today and then we're gonna say
i choose to die and they'd kill us you
know
and that's you know i think all of us
were waiting for this special
ever since we took that vow we're all
waiting for these guys to show up with
knives and
and threaten us but actually we're the
guys with the knives okay we threaten
our bodies off of balance every day
uh we have to we have to make this
decision every day
when we when we decide whether or not to
keep our vows carefully
okay all right uh
it's hard to find those guys who put you
in jail and say i'm going to kill you if
you don't give up your body stuff about
all right uh
the next picture
is see if you can remember i'm going to
give you a minute
to try to remember
this was a reference to uh okay we have
mixed nuts translation
team and we were translating an old
vinaya text
amongst vowels nunsville and
they were talking about the vow the
tradition
uh that we shouldn't
by all when you become a monk or a nun
they give you your robes
they give you a small buddhist statue
and they give you a strainer and in
ancient india you were supposed to carry
this strainer around with you
and when you drink water from a stream
you're supposed to strain the water
first to make sure you don't kill any
small insects
and uh we we mentioned a famous
tradition
in the vinaya that if a couple of monks
go down to the water
down to the stream to get some water
then they should
choose the nicest monk to check the
water
you know don't don't choose the guy who
doesn't care about bugs you know try to
find a guy who loves bugs
and have them check the water okay
because they will be more careful
all right so what's the point and we
talked about
uh kind of ecology vows
where monks and nuns are not supposed to
even
uh pull green leaves off a plant because
there are
these are the homes of tiny creatures
you know so it means respect
even the very small vowels take them
very seriously
because the results multiply
exponentially then it's important to
keep your morality on a very subtle
level
on a very fine level and don't get anal
and i if i was going to write the
bodhisattva house i would write an extra
bodhisattva vowel about
don't get anal about your body's life of
else there's nothing more irritating
than
than a person who informs you they are
keeping their vows
and that's why they have to be [__]
today and
you know so keep your vows sweetly keep
it happily
don't overdo it don't bother other
people with your vows because the vows
are not to bother
the people okay so uh keep the small
vowels
keep them quietly keep them personally
don't advertise it
there's a saying in islam don't the left
hand shouldn't know what the right
shouldn't let the right hand know what
it's doing it means that
don't advertise your vows just keep them
quietly
and keep them on a very fine level okay
next picture
where is that okay
uh this is the idea that uh
being nice to other people is like
planting a a tree oh and today i went to
a peachtree cafe
to check on something and uh
me and stanley and allison planted a
peach tree there
uh when we first started the peachtree
cafe morning show
and i want to tell you guys that three
peaches came out this week
and we got peaches now and
so what it means is take care of your
foundation practices take care of the
root
uh plant nice
by keeping your vows by being nice to
other people and then that's going to
grow into a tree
and that peach tree that we planted five
months ago something
it's already giving a lot of fruit okay
and
if you didn't take care of it when it
was tiny
you wouldn't have anything but if you
take care
of the foundation of your buddhist
practice which is being nice to other
people
then the fruits are going to be
thousands and thousands and thousands
it'll come
it will grow into a huge it'll grow into
a tree
it will give peaches every year and for
many years you will have peaches okay
so keep the protect that this child was
protecting the sprout carefully okay
protect your morality okay all right
next picture
i think if i remember correctly there
were four
conditions that might cause you to break
your commitments okay if you took
bodhisattva commitments or you took
vinaya
prachimaksha commitments or even if you
took diamond way
tantric commitments uh i i think it was
four paw monkey reviewed
no maybe more than that anyway there
were certain conditions
that would help you to break your vows
if you want to break your vows
there's a couple of special ways to do
it okay here's the first one
which is uh if you don't know
what your vowels are then that's a good
way to break them if you want to break
them
then do not study them and and one of my
pet peeves i have many pet dharma peeps
is uh is teachers who give initiations
and in huge initiations and they do not
explain to the
people taking the initiation that they
have just taken vows
and there are hundreds of vows that you
just took when you get an initiation
and you're going to break them if you
don't know them so it's the teacher's
responsibility to
to train you in your vows before you get
an initiation okay
and if they don't offer to train you i
would not take an initiation from them
uh okay so the best way to break your
vows
first way is not to know them okay read
the recipe before you start cooking
that's what veronica tells me every time
i cook
next picture is a lady
saying yeah you know it's not such a big
thing
you know that that vow about i don't
know
uh not cutting green plants without
a prayer come on that's a little extreme
you know
uh that's that's a little too much that
that's not that important i mean couple
bugs
might be using that leaf once in a while
as a roof uh so look it's not that big
of a deal so the second
great way to break your vows is to have
this attitude
like oh that one's not so important i'm
keeping the big ones
okay all right next one
uh if we get a clacia
okay meaning if we get a some kind of
negativity
running around in our mind that's a
great way to break your vows okay
getting irritated with somebody else
or uh getting obsessed with uh
acquiring something money or or you know
getting attached to our netflix at night
uh
those kind of by the way it's not wrong
to watch netflix
but i'm talking about you know
hurting someone else because you want to
get home and watch your nephew that's a
problem okay
so this is called the gang fight
and the story is what
go for the word go for the biggest guy
on the other side okay
uh find out who's the leader of the
other side
and don't talk don't negotiate you know
don't yell at each other walk up to him
and
bash him on the head and then the whole
other side will fall down
okay so identify your worst
bad habit and go after that one first
okay
and that's a way to deal to keep your
mouth
okay next one
if you and uh and by the way
at the age of uh my age okay i'm not
telling you how old i am
but all this young love thing
is so ridiculous from the point of view
of my age
and i can say it with experience because
i had it
but this thing about oh she's the most
beautiful woman in the world
he's the most handsome guy in the world
you know first of all uh my
my older brother he said the funniest
thing he said you like that girl i said
yeah
he said you want to spend your life with
her i said yeah he said
check out her mom first check out how
does her mom look you know
so i go the mom looks terrible she's
overweight she looks
tired and she looks terrible and he says
well what do you think
do you think what do you think she
looked like in the beginning you know so
think about it
you know so don't be if you're attached
to
the the looks of a person or
something physical okay something not
very important about a person that's
going to change
and you will see them get sick you will
see them get old
you will see them have diarrhea throw up
if you're not lucky you will see their
insides and in operations sometime
so you know don't don't fool yourself
that it's worth hurting other people to
get the most beautiful woman or man that
you can
it's it's not worth it okay
it's not it won't last okay all right
you should be
it's great to have a relationship but
have it for the right reason okay
all right next
if you have a problem with anger
or you get upset easily then fantasize
about
giving this person something they would
love to have okay this is called my trai
my tree champa love
okay fantasize try to remember how nice
it is
to give someone something they love
something they want
okay and try to have this attitude if
you feel
if you don't feel friendly towards
another person
then do some fantasies which means
meditation
about giving them something they really
like okay
all right uh next one
is uh i'm gonna give you a moment for
this one i
bet you can't remember what this one is
tim's cheating looking ahead or
something
what was this one okay
this is about pride okay pride
pride is also going to be an obstacle to
keeping your vows
and the most common one of the most
common types of pride
in a monastic situation which is where
this book was taught
generally is uh
how much you know about the scriptures
you know how many
facts have you collected in your
lifetime
and this is something i really enjoy is
obscure dharma facts you know
and and the more you collect uh the more
you feel like you are special
okay and then pablo and prachay said
look
all the dharma you ever learned in your
life all the things you memorized all
the things you debated
all the geshe degrees you could ever
have
compared to what there is still left to
know
you don't know nothing you are like a
a worm on the bottom of the ocean okay
and sometimes go out and look up at the
stars
you know many of those stars have
planets around them
there's people on those planets there's
things to know about those people
there's the things we know
that we're so proud about knowing is a
tiny tiny tiny fraction
of what you could know okay uh
all right so don't have pride
next one
uh one of the big
motivations to break your vows or your
commitments
your morality which is going to stop you
from reaching nirvana
which is going to stop you from reaching
the second
level of the alarm rim personal nirvana
is to understand emptiness study
emptiness
if you realize that the mean things
that someone else is doing to you are
coming directly from what you did
last week then you're not gonna make big
mistakes okay so the more you can study
emptiness
the more you can study cause and effect
uh dependent origination
which means this person's coming from my
seeds
then uh the easier it's gonna be to keep
your vows
okay the easier it's gonna be so study
study study
i had a teacher he said uh
an old inner mongol teacher
very old with tuberculosis and uh
and he he used to say oh yeah he's
very good you are so proud you know you
have such a great amount of pride
uh from princeton and later the geshe
thing
that's a very helpful very helpful uh so
you
you will push yourself harder uh just to
look smart
that's that's lucky but uh later on try
to give it up okay
just just study to be a good person okay
it's like very funny
he gave me adam's text on his deathbed
i remember this okay
next one uh the fourth
this is technically the fourth cause uh
or is it no anyway
uh one of the causes of breaking your
vows or losing your commitment
is that it's very hard in the modern
world
to keep your mind on your vows when
you're very busy
okay when things are moving very fast
and there are a thousand things to see
on the internet
and life is moving so fast and
it's hard to keep that
self-awareness of am i breaking my mouth
you know am i doing anything
to hurt someone you know so you gotta
kind of gotta slow down
come back to your vows and keep some
kind of
uh awareness sensitivity
to the fact that you have commitments
not to hurt other people
okay so the busier things get the more
careful you have to be
all right it's easy to get uh
it's even easy to get irritated with
your partner when you're very busy
you know they they they're trying to
tell you something
and you've got 10 things going on at
work and
and you're like look i don't have time
to listen right now i i i got
i got my boss gave me 10 things to do
you know
and and then those are the times you
have to slow down
and come back to your vows and don't
forget your commitment to be nice to
other people
even when you're very stressed very busy
okay it's better to break a few
business commitments than to
get nervous and stressed and be not nice
to people
it's better to to not pay a bill
or miss a business meeting or or not do
as well as you could in your job
uh if it means keeping your mind clear
okay
all right next picture
this is a lady buying a useless thing in
the store
see if you can remember this story
she said oh this box is so beautiful she
went to the department store
she bought this what is it what's that a
home thing
place you buy stuff crate and barrel
she went to creighton barrel in america
she got this she said oh my husband's
gonna love this box you know
she doesn't have any clue where she's
gonna use it for
but she's gonna take it home
then when she gets home her husband's
gonna say are you crazy
this is a worthless little box we have
enough junk in our house
uh take it back get your money back
now should she go to the gas station
and try to give it back
no that's not where she got the box from
okay i mean it's kind of obvious but we
have to say it
if you buy a stupid box because you like
it and you think your husband's going to
like it which he won't
and he talks you into taking the box
back
you know don't take it back to a
different place take it back to where
you bought it
what's that mean
[Music]
yeah you guys should pay me uh
when it's time to confess when you broke
a vow
then try to get back to the person who
gave you the vow
you know try to try to confess in front
of the person who gave you the vow
is it okay to confess at home by
yourself
not not for vows that you took from
other people
okay in general if you didn't take a vow
from someone else then maybe it's okay
at home
to confess in front of a buddha statue
or something like that
in in extreme cases it's all right but
in general
if you can get back to the person who
gave you your vows
and confess to them openly be be
shameless okay
we're shameless all day so be shameless
about your mouth you know just say oh
what the hell go straight to your
teacher and say i broke this stupid bow
and your teacher's like wow you're a
really bad person and you're like yeah
yeah and get it over with get and then
you feel so clean
you feel so so nice so
you can be shy about lots of things in
your life but don't be shy about your
vows okay if you break a bow
go tell somebody and and that's why you
get rid of it you get rid of the problem
okay if you hold it and hide it if you
spend more work
hiding it then then confessing it or
keeping it
then it's just dumb and and you won't
feel nice
you won't feel clean okay just be open
with your teachers
i i have this problem i have this bad
habit
and uh the karma gets crushed the seed
gets crushed okay
all right and you know your teacher's
gonna say okay okay i heard that before
you told me before
but be persistent okay keep telling them
all right next picture
this is about wait do you remember
again this is about
honoring the small details of valve and
they were talking about
it's actually a valve where monks should
brush their teeth
uh with a stick there was called a sushi
and it was a stick that you were
supposed to use to clean your teeth and
you just cut it off a tree and you use
it you know
and it's a toothbrush and it said
monks should should have their
toothbrushes and you should brush your
teeth
and it might seem like a small thing you
know
wait i'm trying to keep my tantric vow
to go to abitabas paradise
and protect all living beings and buddha
says yeah but in the meantime could you
just please brush your teeth
again everything and you're like but
that's not a really big vow
yeah but it's the small things that make
the buddha paradise
okay it's the small things that
bodhisattvas do
that are nice to other people
course everybody in the world is gonna
you know
i don't know stop a nuclear war or
something if they can
i mean that's obvious but are you a good
enough person
that you don't even want people to smell
your breath
if it might hurt them you see if you're
very sensitive
about tiny things that might hurt other
people
then we can say you're keeping your
morality and
and then it's the small details
that put the finishing touches on your
buddha paradise which you see in the
next picture
uh this is this person uh decorating a
christmas tree
i don't know if i don't even know if you
have ever done a christmas tree but
those of us who grew up in christian
tradition
our parents had us do christmas trees
and
there's something cool about putting on
the last
ornament you know like everybody's
looking at the tree
and they say is it done and they say
yeah it's done
and he said wait there's one more we
should put right there you know so
this is the this christmas tree ornament
is the brushing your teeth okay it's the
small
final details that you put on your
buddha hood
okay it's the small things that
make buddhas it's not the grand things
it's not the big things
it's attention to the small details
of making other people happy that
creates a buddha
okay all right
next one
see if you remember this one i'll give
you a clue a month ago yamantaka
this is a famous alarm rim story uh
so monks and nuns are supposed to go
twice a month to sojung
and confess the mistakes we made to each
other
and openly and
this the teacher said they they struck
the gunty
okay they struck the gunty which is a
special
piece of wood it looks like a 2x4 and
you hit it with a
another stick and it goes
and that's a bell that's an ancient bell
before before
metal was common and they will hit the
hit the plank and when you hear that you
got to go to sojourn
and they still do it i made a gandhi
with my teacher he he wanted one
and we made it to the right there's all
these rules about it
so we and when you hear the gandhi
you're supposed to you hold it here
you hold the gun to here and you hit it
like this
and then all the monks and nuns are
supposed to come for confession
so this teacher said hey they they
struck the gandhi let's go
and the students said no i'm not going
to confess today
and that the teacher's like what because
that's one of the main commitments of a
monk you know
i said go to go to sojourn and the
teacher what are you talking about he
says
i don't have to go today and the teacher
said what do you mean you don't have to
go today he says
you forget you gave me a yamataka
initiation yesterday
i'm yamantaka i'm a buddha i don't need
to go to slowdown anymore
and the teacher grabs him by the hair he
says yeah what the hell
you're yamandika your mother is going to
sojourn with me right now
so what it means is that don't give me
this stuff that you're a great tantica
and you're beyond morality you know now
you have higher
vision uh that's a completely mistaken
idea
okay if you got a
secret initiation then you should be
going to sojourn every morning or
something you should go
more than other people okay because
that's what gives you
that's what gives power to your tantric
practice it's being nice to other people
and confessing when you make a mistake
okay next
uh this is a sad image you know we
always think of
morality as being the roots of our
practice
you know the foundation of our practice
but
uh pabonko and kind of flipped it around
and this is a perfect picture he said
imagine a
an apple tree and someone sliced it in
half
actually he used a palm tree somebody
sliced it
and they cut the top off the tree so
you're not going to get leaves even a
single leaf is not going to come out
so therefore you're not going to get
flowers
and therefore you're not going to get
the fruits which always come from the
flowers
you're not going to get anything okay so
a person
who is not nice to other people day to
day
hour to hour uh they chop off
any chance of of getting those beautiful
fruits of practice
okay all right next one
this was an idea of something that my
teacher asked me
um then i asked my teacher
and i don't know if you remember but i
asked him uh
you know the first of the five paths uh
path of accumulation
uh you reach it when you have a personal
tragedy
but if you're on the bodhisattva track
you reach it when you get body chitter
so i said i don't underst i don't
understand
what's tragic about body china
and he said no no no it's still a theme
of tragedy it's just the tragedy
of every being alive every being in the
in this whole universe is having
the same tragedy and uh
so really that communal tragedy
is the beginning of the five past
thinking about that tragedy
is the beginning of the five pass for a
bodhisattva so really it's the same
the puppy's having a hard time but now
all the puppies in the basket are having
a hard time
and we're all in this together
and that's the beginning of bodhi tuna
okay all right
this uh next picture is a guy
shaking hands with somebody in their
office right
and i don't know i imagine the lady is
introducing them this is joe
he works in the advertising department
and this is sam
he works in the computer department and
they shake hands
do you guys remember what this is
nah uh
it it was a very very cute uh exercise
where we were supposed to close our eyes
and think of the person who irritates us
the most
and see if we could get ourselves upset
you know the problem with this kind of
exercise
is after about 10 minutes you forget
it's an exercise
and you really do get upset let me see
if i can get myself upset
okay how are you gonna do it i'm gonna
think about this guy who gave me a hard
time this week okay go ahead
then you slowly the person starts
shaking you're like what's going on
i got upset the experiment worked you
know
so then the if it's your llama they'll
say
okay check it out how that feels you
know when you
first start thinking about this person
how does it feel
you know what comes up in your heart i
don't know about you
but i get this little glitch in my heart
i start to feel some kind of
discomfort here or here
when i think about a person who's been
bothering me or a problem that's been
bothering me i
i can purposely generate tension
in my inside of myself so he says
let's do an exercise try to try to
trigger some tension in your heart
and then look at that tension and get to
know it you know like as if you're
shaking hands with somebody
get to know what it feels like
when a mental affliction negative
emotion
is first coming up in your heart and
keep practicing it
you know as soon as you feel better and
you forgot about this person then think
of them again
and see if you can get upset again see
if you can start to get upset again
and try to get familiar with what it
feels like shake hands
hi this is geshe michael hi what's
what's your name
oh i'm starting to get upset about this
person oh nice to meet you
now i know what you look like now i can
look out for you
i can avoid you in the future okay all
right
next one
[Music]
it's called visiting the middle of the
sun and
the theme of this lam rim which was
loving the time of the virus
okay
[Music]
the virus is a big thing you know it's
spread across this whole world
you know i've lived a long life and i
thought i saw everything i thought
i kind of entered my 60s and thought
well
now nothing new is going to happen you
know i'm i'm pretty sad for anything
that would happen you know
i've seen everything and nothing can
upset me too much
then this virus shows up and threatens
everybody in the world
and i'm like wow you know that's a big
thing
that covers the whole planet
i don't know if it happened to you but
it happened to me it's probably
bad deed number nine which is ill will
being happy when someone else has a
problem and when i heard that
famous irritating people were getting
sick i was like
i didn't want them to die or anything
but i but i was like yeah
see you know i told you it was bad to be
bad
and then i i caught myself thinking like
that okay so
it feels like a big thing you know it
feels like
this problem has spread all over this
planet
okay and it feels like something then
it's difficult
for me to cope with okay but
we have just entered after 10 years of
long-range study we have just entered
the path for people of greater capacity
and we're going to open that study
with the idea of bodhichitta bodhichitta
what is bodhichina okay
it's not enlightenment mind forget that
lousy trans
incredibly bad translation
it's the wish that i could become a
buddha
to help countless living beings and
there is a direct experience of it in
the same way that there's a direct
experience of emptiness okay there are
there are parallel experiences
that we must get to in this lifetime
and again you should be in meditation
okay so
we describe an extraordinary
what do you call it breakthrough
threshold threshold experience uh
where you go into a deep state of
meditation
and because time and space are coming
from seeds
if you can mess with these seeds then
you can
compact time and space and
in a meditation that's not longer than a
half hour
you could actually visit each person
in the universe including animals and
bugs and birds and fish
and you could communicate with each one
individually within a half an hour
and to each one you could make a
commitment
i mean you meet them you see each one is
suffering each one is uh having a
difficult life
and worried about the future and you
could go to each one separately
and say i got it covered you know just
take it easy i had a guy i used to work
when i was in university i got a
scholarship but they said you just have
to work a few hours a week
and it turned out to be 30 hours a week
and i had to drive a truck
actually first they put me in a
cafeteria and they said
you're going to mop the floor in the
cafeteria i quit within like 10 hours
i quit on the first day and then they
said okay you can drive a truck i said
that's fun i'll drive a truck you know
so i drove a truck for five years
and we had a guy
a permanent university employee
named big john his name was big john
he's this polish guy
seven feet tall huge polish guy
and everyone was afraid when they saw
him they're afraid of him but he was
extremely
sweet and he would bring donuts to work
and he was from trenton
new jersey and trent
and and then he would do the nicest
things for us and he would cover
one day we broke a truck in half we hit
a tree with the truck
and we broke it in half and he covered
for us you know
he's like oh you know these screws
weren't very tight you know and i don't
know what happened the truck fell apart
you know don't blame these guys
don't blame these young guys you know
all they did was driving it you know
and then he'd winked at us and said i
got you coming i got you guys covered
you know so i always think of him when i
think about it
you know so you're going to meet each
living being in the
universe directly and you're going to
say oh
big jug got you covered i got you
covered don't worry
don't worry about it i got you covered
okay
so that's bodhichitta and you should
have that experience you should work for
that experience okay
you have to meditate you have to study
about bodhichitta you have to study the
long room about body tenure
you have to do all those steps like
exchanging yourself and others and then
one day you will have that experience
and you will meet every living being
and you will say to them i got you
covered you don't worry i got you
covered you know what
uh big mike's taking care of you or a
big team or a big stadium
okay i i'm thinking don't worry
don't don't stress out i'm i'm on it
okay and that's exactly what it feels
like it's a personal commitment
all right why are we talking about oh
you're gonna do that on countless worlds
when you do it on the day you do it you
will do it on countless world worlds
okay
an action which is committed directly
with every living creature on countless
worlds
doesn't have trouble taking care of a
single virus
on a single world okay it's nothing a
virus that
endangers seven or eight billion people
is nothing compared to bodhichitta it's
like
it's like we said if you spill ketchup
on your shirt
and you deliver that shirt to the middle
of the sun for 25 million degrees
fahrenheit probably
the ketchup stain is going to disappear
you know
okay you probably don't have to worry
about the kitchen ketchup stain work on
your body china
and you will destroy the virus by the
way by accident okay
all right not a big thing next picture
okay don't mess around with other paths
okay
learn bodhichitta learn to have this
experience
okay don't don't waste your time don't
focus on other things okay focus on
bodhichitta
and then you don't have to do things
twice you know
we talked about doing things twice this
lady's in a rush
she says i don't have time for this body
cheddar stuff
i'm gonna go straight into tantra or you
know
well you're still going to have to come
back and pick up that thing you forgot
okay which is bodhichitta so
so work on your body cheddar first okay
don't
don't start don't have to drive back
home and pick up the body chatter and
come back
okay all right
then this was a radical example the next
picture
and this is a hard one to remember okay
i'm going to give you a second to think
about it
i don't know if you remember this but um
this is kind of complicated uh a group
of 60 guys
and girls was about to achieve nirvana
just by seeing emptiness directly and
without bodhichitta
lower nirvana and then manjusri shows up
and teaches them about bodhichitta maybe
he thought about this experience we just
talked about
and they were all irritated by manjushri
they're like don't waste our time
we are close to nirvana we can feel it
we can taste it
we all saw emptiness already you know
don't waste our time
don't don't don't talk to us about this
stuff okay
and uh then because they had
disrespected the teaching on bodhichitta
they went to the health
they didn't get the they didn't get to
uh
nirvana they dropped to the hell realms
and but they burned it off and they
became humans
again after many millions of years and
deep down inside was his teaching that
madhusha had given them about
bodhichitta and they remembered it
and they got to be bodhisattvas and they
became buddhists
and that would take less time
than going into a lower nirvana without
studying bodhichitta okay it would take
it would be faster to go to hell
and come back and start over again
with bodhichitta than if you didn't use
body cheddar and you went to a lower
nirvana
okay so this is a picture
of somebody sending somebody the wrong
way on purpose
okay this lady is asking
where is that superhighway that goes to
the store i want to visit
and the guy knows the highway is blocked
so he tells her listen don't go that way
that highway's blocked go the other way
and she said she insists no tell me
where's the highway i want
then he lies to her and he says oh
oh take this way it's actually the long
way
that he wanted her to go anyway so
so this is a story about skillful means
okay next picture
this is warming up before you run a race
uh usually we
we use this image about what do you guys
remember
it's a breath meditation okay usually
we say look breath meditation is just
warming up don't
don't think it's the race they don't
have in the olympics
a contest for stretching before the race
is okay there's not much
you don't get a gold medal for
stretching okay
but in this case we're not talking about
breath meditation
we're talking about uh it is good
to do the three principle paths in order
okay you know get sad about this world
you know struggle to have that body to
the experience directly
and then see emptiness so you can help
everybody okay so
warm up with the first feelings of
sadness about this life
okay now uh next picture
and we're almost done i think we very
close are we close
not that close okay uh
do you remember who these guys are they
are a very uh lousy band
you know i guess you met them in
shopping malls or something
singing bad songs uh and uh
they're called the opening act okay so
the steps of the path
for lesser capacity you know trying to
get to a higher rebirth
the steps of the path for medium
capacity trying not to come back to this
world at all and then the steps of the
path for greater capacity
these two levels are just the opening
act
and this is the main thing getting to
bodhichitta
what's above body china
there's six perfections okay so so check
it out
steps of the past to keep your rear end
out of the lower rails
steps of the path to get to nirvana
and then we got bodhichitta this
experience
of meeting every living being and making
a commitment that i'll take care of i'm
gonna take care of you
and then up here is the sixth okay this
is six in chinese okay
up here is the six perfections okay
now which of these is the big thing
which is the real band which is the
opening act
okay these guys obviously you know lower
nirvana not such a big deal
but what's interesting is uh pabokkar
and pache says
that experience with every living being
is the is the main act that's what i
want you to focus on
i want you to try to have that
experience if you have that experience
we can talk about
the six perfections including number six
which is
seeing emptiness okay you know let's
talk about that later
come on i want you guys to focus on
having this experience okay
by the way a good way to have that
experience is to imagine that experience
try listen to the description of it
and pretend you can do it and keep
pretending
keep doing it and you know
it it feels like a slot machine i like
to say it feels like a slot machine
so when you push a slot machine these
pictures
roll up cherries right and other things
and i mean not that i ever play this
obviously okay well once with my dad
you push the lever and then these dials
come like this so just imagine
that your mother's face comes up
and you say mom you look worried and
she's like yeah i'm worried about life
and say don't worry big john's got you
covered
you know just calm down i got it i i i'm
on it
then your dad's picture comes up
not just the picture the person comes up
and then it feels like that in
meditation so try to imagine it
try to practice it okay and it will
trigger the real thing
it will trigger the real thing bring
people up one by one
look at how they feel make a commitment
don't worry i got you covered i'm on it
then they pass then bring up another
person
and practice that way you can do five or
six people
and then it'll get faster because time
will change
okay all right that's the and
and pabonko was just saying that's the
main show
that's the rolling stones the rest is
just
you know new bands that aren't very good
and then i don't know who's at the end
they have an ending act not usually
anyway the rest is just leaving the
stadium or something don't worry about
it
okay all right now we crossed over
into the 10 cool things about getting
bodhichitta
we will only have time to do the first
one in this long room
and the first cool thing about getting
bodhichitta is
if you have been a nerdy kid
playing tennis in the school and your
dream was to be
on the team then next picture
no yeah then here's the gesture michael
in the middle
on top okay not the weirdos below
uh then you can
you can be on the team and it's cool to
be on the team of buddy stop bus
it's you know work to be on that team
and it's it's so uh cool
to be on that team because that team
stretches across the universe
and it's all done cool people in the
whole universe so
it's nice to be part of that team it's
sweet
okay uh that was the first benefit
of bodhichitta now next picture
this is a guy visiting an art museum and
he talked about the two levels of tantra
first level
uh meet angels
second level study from them how to be
an angel and become an
angel okay and in the first level we're
supposed to actually mean
real angels in person and it's not
like standing in an art museum and
looking
at a statue or a tonka
of a person it's meeting the person
directly
and that's totally completely different
thing right
if you try to practice tantra without
that bodhichitta experience
then it will be like looking at pictures
of buddhas
instead of meeting buddhas okay they
don't like to talk to people
who don't have bodhichitta all right
they feel more comfortable
around people who've had this experience
so try to have this experience
and then tantra is going to work for you
and if you don't have this experience
don't just it's going to be difficult
it's going to be like
looking at pictures of buddhists instead
of hanging out with buddha okay
all right next one
if you try to practice tantra without
bodhichitta you might have
bad results and we talked about the
first nuclear test
in modern times and
the scientists admitted that it
this explosion might start the whole
world on fire
and so they were just trying to do
something cool
but they were taking a chance of a huge
disaster
that's tantra without body chitter okay
that's like
setting the whole sky on fire by
accident you will you will mess up
okay all right next one
uh even a small neutral
karmas become powerful for a person with
bodhichitta a person with bloody
children can feed a bird
make a prayer about it and it affects
millions of people okay they have this
power
next picture
even small bad deeds like stealing a
french fry to give it to a bird
could be powerful if done by a
bodhisattva
uh but it's dangerous practice okay we
are not
at that level we are not at that level
we are not at that level
did you hear that no uh and we had a
picture
of a fugu fish and
you know people in japan like macho guys
they
eat this fish it has very
very poisonous parts of it that can kill
you immediately 50 people a year die in
japan
but people still go to the restaurant
and to serve this fish in a restaurant
you need three years of special training
or you will kill somebody
and that's the same with stealing a
french fry to give it to a burn
because you want to help the bird so
we're not at that level don't try to eat
food fish
if you're not trained okay
then we had a nice picture of nick and
aaron
with their their boss their big boss
which is amelie hi emily
and uh amelie represents the buddha
and nick represents uh the father
which is bodhichitta and aaron
represents
uh wisdom which is the direct perception
of emptiness
and in a certain way
somehow i don't know what this belief is
in asia but in a certain way the data is
irreplaceable
uh something special about the dad
i don't know what it is but anyway
emptiness you can see on different
levels right
uh on all three tracks uh but
bodhichitta you got to be a special
person
you can only see it on the highest track
okay it defines you
as a higher track person okay all right
and you need both to have your baby
which is buddhahood
next picture uh
yeah we said took time to kill
to tell which tim correctly identified
today as
what's your main practice you know
what's what's the thing
that's number one in your life right now
like hey until the next alarm rim the
medicine buddha
in october uh look i want you guys to
treat this as your main practice try to
have
that experience of meeting countless
beings try to have that experience i
don't care
if you sit there hour after hour and
nothing happens
just try just pretend just go over it in
your mind
until the next one room okay let's let's
make a deal like that
okay make it your main practice
all right next picture
if that practice wasn't so important
then one of the greatest buddhists of
all time lord atesha would not have
sailed for 13 months at the risk of his
life to get the teachings on bodhisattva
that you just got
on this video okay and you didn't have
to go anywhere
so okay if adrisha thought it was worth
risking his life
for 13 months in a tiny ship
you know on the pacific ocean and the
indian ocean then
maybe it's important you know maybe
maybe it's worth it okay all right next
picture
uh i think the dumbest thing you can do
in your whole life
is to go to paris and not buy a
croissant
okay i'm just saying you know probably
there's other dumb things you can do in
your life but
to me the ultimate dumb is to go to
paris and not to go to a belonging you
know
or at least buy a clip
on the street with the what's that
chocolate stuff stuff
nutella yeah don't have a nutella crepe
okay like go to paris and don't have a
nutella cream
then that proves you're like crazy okay
so
uh if you're studying lumran
if you got this fire in the alarm room
and guess what's been teaching it for 10
years
and you finally get to the croissant
which is the buddhist chili experience
don't be
crazy and leave paris without eating it
okay don't leave
lamrim without getting this experience
you'd be an idiot
okay all right and
we're finished with a croissant i think
you want to make a presentation
no i was guessing there might be a
croissant in that bank
okay tim lowenhout is going to make
the formal presentation to geshila
my payment oh oh it's a pandey
pandey what do you call it
what's that called
panda chocolate panda chocolate okay
here you gotta split it into three parts
and give me all three i mean no just one
thing
okay so i got the panda chocolate
uh this is what you give to your teacher
when they teach you about buddhism
and okay so let's make a deal uh
for the next couple of months work on
that experience do the dedication
chapter
in your meditation of shantida and
try to work on having that experience
the worst thing that can happen
that at least you will plant seeds in
your mind to have the experience okay so
just
just pretend just sit down and fantasize
about it
fantasizing is good meditation okay
fantasize that you had this experience
of meeting
one by one every living being and you
make a
you made a personal commitment with each
one
to take care of them in an ultimate way
okay
all right see you in the next alarm rim
for medicine buddha yay